Luca Nenna

Personal Information Born on September, 18, 1988 in Brescia.

Italian and French citizen https://lucanenna.github.io

Laboratoire de Mathématiques d'Orsay Bâtiment 307 Faculté des Sciences d'Orsay Université Paris-Saclay

F-91405 Orsay Cedex, France luca.nenna@universite-paris-saclay.fr

RESEARCH INTERESTS Optimal Transport, Calculus of Variations, Numerical Analysis, Mathematical Physics, Mathematical Economics.

CURRENT POSITION

Septembre 2018-now

• Maître de conférences at Université Paris-Saclay (LMO) .

September 2017-August 2018

• Post-doc (CNRS) under the supervision of Mathieu Lewin.

October 2016-August 2017,

• Ater at Université Paris-Dauphine, Paris.

EDUCATION

Université Paris-Dauphine and I.N.R.I.A., Paris, France

Ph.D., Mathematics, 5th December 2016

- Thesis: Numerical methods for Multi-Marginal Optimal Transportation
- Advisors: Jean-David Benamou and Guillaume Carlier
- Referees: Prof. Alfred Galichon (NYU) and Prof. Dejan Slepčev (CMU)
- Dissertation committee: J-D. Benamou, G. Carlier, Y. Brenier, M. Lewin, C. Léonard, V. Ehrlacher and D. Slepčev.

Politecnico di Milano, Milan, Italy

Master Degree in Mathematical Engineering (110/110), April 2013

- Thesis Topic: Finite element discretization for large eddy simulation of turbulent flows
- Advisor: Lorenzo Valdettaro

Bachelor in Mathematical Engineering, September 2010

- (Reading course) Topic: Tornadogenesis
- Advisor: Paolo Biscari

Publications

- Benamou, Jean-David and Carlier, Guillaume and Cuturi, Marco and Nenna, Luca and Peyré, Gabriel, Iterative bregman projections for regularized transportation problems, SIAM Journal on Scientific Computing, 37, 2, A1111—A1138, 2015, Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics.
- 2. Benamou JD., Carlier G., **Nenna L.** (2016) A Numerical Method to Solve Multi-Marginal Optimal Transport Problems with Coulomb Cost. In: Glowinski R., Osher S., Yin W. (eds) Splitting Methods in Communication, Imaging, Science, and Engineering. Scientific Computation. Springer, Cham.

- 3. Di Marino, S., Gerolin, A., **Nenna, L.** (2017). 9. Optimal transportation theory with repulsive costs. Topological Optimization and Optimal Transport (pp. 204-256). Berlin, Boston: De Gruyter. Retrieved 30 Jan. 2018, from https://www.degruyter.com/view/books/9783110430417/9783110430417-010/9783110430417-010.xml
- 4. Blanchet, A., Carlier, G., **Nenna, L.** Vietnam J. Math. (2018) 46: 15. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10017-0255-x
- 5. M. Seidl, S. Di Marino, A. Gerolin, **L. Nenna**, K. Giesbertz , P. Gori-Giorgi, *The strictly-correlated electron functional for spherically symmetric systems revisited*, jhal-01469822;, to appear on Physical Review A.
- JD Benamou, G. Carlier, L. Nenna, Generalized incompressible flows, multimarginal transport and Sinkhorn algorithm, Numerische Mathematik 142 (1), 33-54, 2019.
- JD Benamou, G. Carlier, S. Di Marino, L. Nenna, Quadratic Mean Field Games and Entropic Minimization, Mathematical Models and Methods in Applied Sciences 29 (08), 1553-1583, 2019.
- 8. L. Nenna and B. Pass, Variational problems involving unequal dimensional optimal transport, Journal de Mathématiques Pures et Appliquées, 2020.

Papers in Preparation

- 1. L. Nenna, B. Pass, A note on Cournot-Nash equilibria and unequal dimension.
- 2. L. Nenna, B. Pass, A class of metrics on the space of probability measures.
- 3. M. Seidl, S. Di Marino, A. Gerolin, **L. Nenna**, K. Giesbertz , P. Gori-Giorgi, *The strictly-correlated electron functional for spherically symmetric systems revisited II: SGS CONJECTURE*.
- 4. Di Marino, S., Gerolin, A., **Nenna, L.** Diagonal estimates for minimizers of the Levy-Lieb functional.
- 5. S. Di Marino, M. Lewin, L. Nenna, Grand Canonical Optimal Transport.

PRESENTATIONS Talks and Poster

- Schrödinger Problem and Mean-field PDE Systems: Computational and Theoretical Advances, CIRM, November 2021
- Schrödinger's problem and Optimal Transport, Lisbon, September 2021.
- Seminar at School of Applied Mathematics, FGV, Rio, December 2020.
- Analysis Seiminar at TUM, Munich, July 2020.
- FGS'19, Nice, September 2019.
- People in Optimal Transportation and Applications, Cortona, June 2019.
- SPO seminar, IHP, Paris, April 2019.
- Optimal Transport tools in Density Functional Theory, BIRS, Banff, February 2019.
- MokaMeeting. Inria-Paris January 2019.
- From Stochastic Geometric Mechanics to Mass Transportation problems, University of Lisbon, Lisbon, 3 septembre 2018.
- Seminar CalVa, University Paris-Sud, Orsay, 26 mars 2018.
- Session on Mean Field Games, PgmoDays, Paris, 14 November 2017.
- Mean Field Games, IPAM (UCLA), Los Angeles, 29 August 2017.
- Seminar of Applied Mathematics, University of Alberta, Edmonton, 21 July 2017.

- Optimal Transport meets Density Functional Theory, University of Jyväskylä, Jyväskylä, 1-7 June 2017.
- Optimal Transport and PDEs, GSSI, L'Aguila, 6-7 April 2017.
- Numerical Analysis Seminar, CERMICS, École des Ponts, Paris, 17 November 2016.
- MAD-Stat Seminar, Toulouse School of Economics, Toulouse, 3 November 2016.
- Computational Optimal Transportation, CRM, Montréal, July 2016.
- Smai-MODE congress, ENSEEIHT, Toulouse, March 2016.
- Numerical Analysis and PDEs seminar, Université Paris Sud-Orsay, Orsay, February
- Ceremade Young Researchers seminar, Université Paris-Dauphine, Paris, February
- Workshop Optimal Transport: Aspects Numériques et Applications, IMB, Bordeaux, October 2015.
- Young Researchers Summer School, Raveau, September 2015.
- Mini-workshop: DFT and optimal transport with Coulomb cost, VU university, Amsterdam, August 2015.
- SMAI congress, poster "OPTIMAL TRANSPORT AND DENSITY FUNCTIONAL THEORY", Les Karellis, June 2015.
- Matinée des doctorants, Université Paris-Dauphine, Paris, May 2015.
- Inria's Junior Seminar, I.N.R.I.A., Rocquencourt, March 2015
- Optimal Transport in the Applied Sciences, Ricam (JKU), Linz, December 2014.
- MokAlien 1st Meeting, McGill University, Montreal, October 2014.
- Numerical Optimal Transport, Université Paris-Dauphine, Paris, September 2014.

RESEARCH VISITS

- University of Alberta, Edmonton, 24/08-08/09 2019 (collaboration avec Brendan
- University of Alberta, Edmonton, 05/07-15/07 2018 (collaboration avec Brendan Pass).
- University of Alberta, Edmonton, 09/07-30/07 2017 (collaborator: Brendan Pass).
- MFO, Oberwolfach, 22/01 04/02 2017, "Research in Pairs" program with Simone Di Marino and Augusto Gerolin.

AWARDS AND FUNDING

- Young Research prize 2017 (Fondation Paris Dauphine and Accuracy).
- PEDR 2020-2024
- PEPS CNRS, 5k €

OTHER ACTIVITIES Article reviewing for:

- Journal Of Optimization Theory and Applications.
- SIAM Journal on Mathematical Analysis.
- Mathematics of Operations Research.
- Journal of Global Optimization.
- SIAM Journal on Scientific Computing.
- ESAIM: Mathematical Modelling and Numerical Analysis.
- M3AS.

Teaching EXPERIENCE

Université Paris-Saclay

- A.Y. 2021-22 • Numerical Analysis for EDO (3rd year CM);
- Optimization (3rd year TD+TP):
- Optimization (M1-Ensta TD+TP);
- Optimization (M1-MA CM+TD+TP);
- Numerical Analysis for PDE (M1-MFA CM+TD+TP);

• Optimal Transport (M2-Optimization CM): Université Paris-Saclay A.Y. 2020-21 • Numerical Analysis for EDO (3rd year CM+TD+TP); • Optimization (3rd year TD+TP); • Optimization (M1-Ensta TD+TP); • Optimization (M1-MA CM+TD+TP); • Numerical Analysis for PDE (M1-MFA CM+TD+TP): • Optimal Transport (M2-Optimization CM); Université Paris-Sud A.Y. 2019-20 • Numerical Analysis for EDO (3rd year TD+TP); • Optimization (3rd year TD+TP); • Optimization (M1-Ensta TD+TP); • Optimization (M1-MA CM+TD+TP); • Numerical Analysis for PDE (M1-MFA TD+TP); • Optimal Transport (M2-Optimization); Université Paris-Sud A.Y. 2018-19 • Numerical Analysis for EDO (3rd year CM+TD+TP); • Optimization (3rd year TD+TP); • Optimization (M1-Ensta TD+TP); • Optimization (M1-MA CM+TD+TP); • Numerical Analysis (M1-MFA TD+TP); Teaching Assistant (Université Paris-Dauphine) A.Y. 2016-17 • Calculus II (1st year); • Calculus III (2nd year); • Numerical Analysis (2nd year); Teaching Assistant (Université Paris-Dauphine) 2nd semester 2015–16 • Numerical Analysis (2nd year); • Numerical Analysis: Optimization (3rd year) Teaching Assistant (Université Paris-Dauphine) 2nd semester 2014-15• Numerical Analysis (2nd year): • Numerical Analysis: Optimization (3rd year) Computer Programming: SOFTWARE SKILLS • C, C++, MATLAB, Maple, FreeFem++, Julia, Python.

Languages

HARDWARE AND

- Italian (Mother Tongue);
- English (Fluent);
- French (Fluent).